[Music]
welcome to around the Empire the show
that takes you around the u.s. Empire
i'm your host Dan right I'm your co-host
ome up on today's episode January
eighteen to twenty seventeen we speak
with former CIA officer John Kiriakou
but before we do that here is around the
Empire we begin leaf- Africa Command
standing US interest in Africa carlyle
group will control South Africa's
largest credit agency the carlyle group
with 169 billion dollars in assets as a
u.s. buyout fund and will become the
largest shareholder for global credit
ratings south africa's largest
pan-african rating agency call our group
is one of the largest private equity
funds associated with the Bush family as
well as you bin Laden family and others
us has an increasing role throughout the
continent and is now in over 20
countries with special forces operations
on to United States European Command
Ukraine officials are quote scrambling
to make amends with the president-elect
after quietly working to boost Clinton
Kent Vogel and david stern of political
europe say that ukrainian efforts to
sabotage Trump have backfired Alexander
lupa a Ukrainian American former Clinton
administration employee and former DNC
staffer work on opposition research
against trumping coordinated with the
ukrainian embassy the DNC told POLITICO
that you did it all on our own and not
out their direction since we believe
that one European ex-leader sent a
letter to warn Trump against restoring
relations with and lifting sanctions on
Russia they try to convince trumpets
somehow a deal with Putin will not bring
peace on the contrary makes war more
likely not exactly a logical argument
now on to the United States Pacific
Command in an interview with The Wall
Street Journal president-elect Donald
Trump call now president so that
everything is open to negotiation with
US policy on China including the one
China policy on Taiwan China's foreign
minister Wang Yi told Hong Kong media
that quote the one-china principle is a
cornerstone of the healthy development
of sino-us relations and we do not want
any interference
destruction of this political foundation
Trump mock the fact of the u.s. old two
billion dollars in arms of Taiwan but
can't accept a congratulatory phone call
from the head of state the statement on
Taiwan issued by the Chinese Foreign
Minister Liu Kang left no room for doubt
quote the one-china principle is
non-negotiable all into the United
States Southern Command and Cuba a
flurry of small deals put in place
before Tom takes office Cuba and foreign
partners began drilling for oil in the
Gulf of Mexico and there are concerns
that the US would not be able to
participate in oil spill responses
because of remaining sanction a quote
oil spill pact was signed by the Obama
administration the Cuban government to
prepare joint disaster plans test them
and train personnel among other measures
this is one of the flurry of small deals
in recent weeks being put in place
before the trump administration takes
control since tom has threatened to
scrap still fragile state on between the
two countries and less Cuba makes
further political and economic
concessions moving along the united
states central command in iraq the army
of advancing rapidly in Lhasa the Iraqi
army is advancing and now is in quote
striking distance of Saddam Hussein's
presidential palace in law school this
is the first time in nearly two and a
half years of the government forces have
seen the site Kevin barren of Defense
one recalls many conversations with
troops and officers of the US military
base without name in air bill they
helped formulate them and what to
continue the Obama doctrine in which the
US and coalition forces fight Isis by
with and through local forces and at a
patient pace Baron noted that the covert
based at Kurdistan international airport
is growing into a permanent base quoted
seems the US military is in Iraq to stay
and photos and so they are temporary
quarters are being replaced with
permanent buildings to accommodate quote
American forces including special
operators CIA agents and private
military contractors in Afghanistan more
Marines deployed the Helmand 300 Marines
from Camp Lejeune will deploy to Helmand
province in Afghanistan to advise and
assist the Afghan forces struggling
against the Taliban which control
eighty-five percent of the province now
a year ago was controlled only twenty
percent Helmand is the province where
most of the poppies for heroin are grown
Marines left this province in
Afghanistan as part of the President
Obama's promised 2014 withdraw some of
the three hundred Marines have been
deployed here before and some will stay
at Camp Leatherneck which was turned
over to the Afghan forces in 2014 and
finally to the United States Northern
Command the homefront the latest dirty
dossier stunned by the media and US
intelligence on Trump State Department
veteran Peter Van Buren who was
retaliated against for reading the book
criticizing reconstruction project in
Iraq notice that the latest done against
president Trump by the US intelligence
community leaders has quote collapse
like a paper bag in the rain a senior
intelligence official told NBC that the
salacious opposition research addendum
to the dossier used in the alleged
Russian act briefing last week was not
given the Trump nor was included in an
oral briefing from dispute about that
numerous US media outlets CNN and others
such as New York Times claimed that the
chief of Americans intelligence agencies
naturally presented both President Obama
and president Trump's and
president-elect romp with a summary of
unsubstantiated reports that Russia had
collected compromising his hellacious
personal information about mr. Trump
Trump reacted by blaming the
intelligence agencies for leaving the
fake news quote-unquote addendum to the
classified data and by saying on Twitter
quote are we living in Nazi Germany the
Kremlin spokesman denied the claim that
Russia didn't have the material and
called a story a fake information as
fabrication this is pulp fiction the
name of the former British spy who
prepared the dirty dossier christopher
david steele formerly of mi6 was
revealed but he was given time to flee
his home and go into hiding before the
revelation according to the Telegraph
news media steel is the co-founder of
Orbis business intelligence limited and
was hired by a firm in Washington first
by Trump's Republican enemies and then
by Democrats back in Hillary Clinton who
quote shopped it to the media still
spent months shopping his flawed
intelligence dossier the US media but
now that his identity has been revealed
in the US media what to talk to him he
refuses to comment surprise surprise
things are stirred up all over and
Britain as well British intelligence are
helping steal hive Nigel Farage one time
you Kip leader Kingdom Independence
Party says they shouldn't help them in
the BBC security correspondent Frank
garden air claim the dodgy dossier
wasn't so dodgy when it was written and
didn't have the bad spelling and
quotient ludicrous scenarios suggesting
that it was the Yanks that rewrote it
unquote according to the account of BBC
reporting from a comment sir British
media headlines referred to the whole
affair has the dirty dossier The
Telegraph reports that Whitehall and
downing street were aware of the dossier
the Russian embassy in London tweeted
debt Christopher steel still works for
mi6 fifth days ago Russia claimed they
knew of an impending official anti
Russia witch-hunt involving the British
special services and my six Chiefs are
distancing themselves from Christopher
steal the sun tabloid reported according
to anonymous sources one senior
intelligence source called him an idiot
early on the Guardian reporter that's
well-known uber Hawks Senator John
McCain past documents of the FBI
director McCain says he was informed
about the existence of documents
separate by an intermediary from a
Western allied state who that could be
dispatched on emissary missions overseas
McCain once a special select Senate
committee to be formed to investigate
Trump in his elections connections could
be Kremlin he can't get his way than he
says he would use the Armed Services
Committee he chairs and other committees
ones sea2 Director of National
Intelligence James clapper issued a
public statement reporting that he had
called Trump and denounced the media
leaks as quote extremely corrosive and
damaging to our national security said
he believed that the intelligence
community and not least the material to
the media and that Congress had these
materials before the intelligence
community
the CIA is mouthpiece at the Washington
Post David Ignatius published not bad on
January 12th where he alleged that about
intercepts between the tenant general
now National Security Advisor Mike Flynn
and the Russian ambassador in an update
Ignatius as the Trump campaign told him
that Flynn offered condolences for the
killing of the Russian ambassador in
Turkey and for the shoot-down of a
Russian plane carrying acquire Ignatius
did appearances on PBS newshour with the
same messaging and on embassy embassy
during which an audio which caused him
to repeat the word Russia Russia Russia
again into his feed so did someone at
the CIA leak to ignatius who is leaking
these dossiers and floating them around
in other words what on earth is going on
at the CIA well famous whistleblower
John Kerry aku tells us
[Music]
and that was around the Empire today on
the show is former CIA officer john
kerry aku who has a recent article and
reader supporter news titled i have come
to the conclusion the country does not
need a CIA John's gonna talk with us
today about the article and his thoughts
on the TA I going done hey doing well
thanks how are you great so I wanted to
just lead off with this paragraph in the
article that struck me quote we can
certainly have a discussion about
whether or not the country even need the
CIA I have come to the conclusion that
it does not the excellent civil servants
in the State Department's Bureau of
intelligence and research can do the
analysis the Pentagon's defense Human
Services can recruit and run human
sources around the world a myriad of VOD
and other civilian offices and bureaus
can do the science and technology
development and I couldn't help us think
when i read that of the book i read that
i highly recommend everybody called
legacy of ashes oh yes which is which is
actually a quote from President
Eisenhower who I guess at the end of his
presidency figured out that he the
Dulles brothers had kind of been running
him around and said that he was leaving
to his well we now know John Kennedy a
legacy of ashes so can you talk about
just that I were just my basic like do
we need a CIA and what if these other
services can be performed by other
agencies as you noted should we just end
it I think we should just end it I'm
certainly not the first person to say
this at a President Eisenhower said it
President Kennedy Senate just said it
just two weeks before he was
assassinated Senator Daniel Patrick
Moynihan the late senator from the state
of New York wrote a book about it in
1976 and said that the CIA should be
disbanded and its responsibilities
scattered around government but it's
kind of an interesting story from the
time of the CIA's creation in 1947 with
the passage of the National Security Act
J Edgar Hoover went to President Truman
to argue against this new law that would
create the CIA
and Truman assured him that CIA would
not be a standalone agency well with
that whoever just assumed that the CIA
would become a department within the FBI
and that he would end up leading it it
did not and Hoover had historically
correlations with General Bill Donovan
Wild Bill Donovan and immediately the
competition between the CIA and the FBI
began it got worse through the 1950s
particularly with the overthrow of
Masonic in Iran with CIA interventions
in Latin America it continued to worsen
through the 60s in Vietnam through the
70s I mean you look anywhere around the
world and you can see these failed CIA
interventions you know this this failed
CIA intervention in Iran in 19 in the
1950s that overthrew a democratically
elected prime minister has led to a
foreign policy crisis that here we are
more than a half a century later we
still haven't gotten through it look at
look at Greece which is which is both a
NATO member and a European Union member
and the Greek people still have not
gotten past the trauma that was the
7-year military dictatorship installed
by henry kissinger in the CIA i have an
attorney who was one of President
Reagan's assistant attorneys general in
the early 1980s and he maintains that
the CIA has never succeeded in anything
that it's done it has missed everything
from the worst thing of the Vietnam War
to the fall of the Soviet Union to the
al-qaeda attacks of 2001 it's never
gotten anything right so when do we
finally declare that the experiment has
failed and it's time to move on I'd
right I could come I mean that makes a
strong case and I mean being former said
I want to go too far to what
but you did work in Greece at one point
if i'm correct spent two years in greece
and it does seem like when the CIA
intervenes right what's that what are
the winds what are the actual but what
it does seem to be able to do it maybe
we can talk about this is there seem to
be very good at putting a good face on
their failures or burying their failures
and it that's one of the parts of that
phrase legacy of ashes is there so good
at hiding it that apparently there was
operations going to North Korea they
would parachute people in they get
immediately captured and killed it was a
complete waste of time but they were
able to bury it so is that the key to
why they haven't been abolished yet is
they are able to hide their failure so
well well I think that's a part of it
they are able to hide their failures
very well there are also masters at
behind the scenes public relations
Nicholas shoe just came out with a book
in the past year about CIA activities in
Hollywood and how the CIA has
successfully recruited major a-list
Hollywood directors producers and
writers to essentially tell an inflated
false CIA story of victory and progress
and patriotism when in fact none of that
is true one of the great things about
legacy of ashes I thought was the CIA's
response to it the author whiner Tim Tim
whiner I think his name was won the
Pulitzer Prize for legacy of ashes and
after he was awarded the pulitzer prize
the CIA came out with a statement saying
that the book was unfair because the
CIA's successes has to remain classified
right so as not to expose far as this
method I always used to lastway they'd
say that they've said it for years
whereas the CIA's failures are
frequently declassified and that's the
only information that's available to
scholars well that's nonsense the truth
of the matter is this is dia frequently
failed at what it's supposed to do you
know I've said many many times in the
press and the public that the CIA job is
very very simple twofold one is to
recruit
spies to steal secrets and two it is to
use the information from those spies to
craft the best possible intelligence to
inform policy making so that
intelligence goes to the President the
Vice President the Secretary of State
and Defense the head of the National
Security Council those the primary
policy makers who are the consumers of
CIA information but if the information
is bad it leads to bad policy decisions
and we have seen Matt since the Truman
administration right and in Truman's
original as i understand it his original
idea was he just wanted like a newspaper
that he could read and that was really
the end he wasn't a lot of covert
operations it was just like I went
analysis and it is what it was it was an
actual classified newspaper that was
delivered to the president every morning
you're right well then we've paired to a
veered off course and I guess that's
where your own story comes in part of
the reason I think they're so well known
to the people who read firedoglake and
now reach shatterproof is you were
prosecuted for exposing or allegedly
exposing whatever oh the torture program
of the CIA ran that has been questioned
you talk about Hollywood and zero dark
thirty it seems like they're they're
very vigilant about protecting some
secrets like that these are also at
least today and this is where I want to
kind of talk about John Brennan there's
also seem to be very okay with leaking
things that hurt certain politicians
they don't like or am I perhaps miss
reading these leaks in the proud there's
a CIA released with impunity when those
leaks have the support of the White
House or when the leaks make the
administration look good it's always
been that way if this is not unique to
the Obama administration almost
certainly there have been some
incredible least through the course of
the Obama administration that we're
never prosecuted and and before I really
get the job rented I'll tell you Leon
Panetta when I wrote my first book it
took me nine months to write and it took
me 22 months to get it cleared I ended
up
having to take out 72 ages and when all
was said and done the CIA asked the
Justice Department's file of felony
charge density for the book they didn't
do that I was never charged and I didn't
even realize that until I was arrested
on other charges later leon panetta
wrote a memoir and didn't like the pace
of the clearance process and he said
screw it and he sent it to the publisher
and it was published with all of its top
secret classified information attack
well Leon Panetta was never charged with
a crime Leon Panetta wasn't even sued in
civil court which the CIA does quite
frequently where someone publishes a
book that's not been cleared the CIA
successfully sued to recoup all of the
prophets and the book advance they do
that all the time they didn't do that to
Leon Panetta so you know if you if
you've got four shiny stars on your
shoulder or if you're a friend of the
President or you make the president look
good you can leak whatever you want and
there's not going to be any any problem
for you if you could spy on the Senate
and you can attack directly into the
Senate's computers and then say that it
was deceitful but they made you do it
and you're still going to get up I've
known John Brennan for 27 years I've
never liked John Brennan John Brennan
didn't like me I had no respect for John
Brennan but he does have an interesting
backstory and he has very very good
political skills John Brennan was what I
was hired in in January of 1990 in the
CIA's Directorate of intelligence that's
the analytic side John was a mid-level
manager he was in the well I won't say
where he was working on the Middle
Eastern event ellipses John did not get
along with his supervisor who was really
a legendary figure in CIA analysis she
was extensively published she was well
known around town they didn't like each
other and John went to her and asked for
her support in his in to enter into the
CIA's senior intelligence service that's
sis that's the executive levels of the
CIA
she told him that not only would he
never be in the senior intelligence
service but she didn't even want him
working for her anymore and he was fired
so when you are forced out of a job at
the CIA you have six weeks to find
another job and if you don't find a job
in those six weeks you are actually
fired so John immediately began pounding
the pavement looking for a job well this
was around Christmas time and jobs
normally open up in the summer there
aren't many jobs open at Christmas time
so finally he ended up going to the
president's Daily Brief staff the PDD
stuff and said look I really need a job
and as it happened there was one job
open and that was to be the PDD briefer
for the lowest ranking person entitled
to a pd debriefing and that was the
director of intelligence program at the
National Security Council who at the
time happened to be George Tenet so John
and George immediately hit it off
they're both big loud ugly non-smoking
alpha dogs and they hit it off John
would go to the White House give the
briefing there used to be a cigar shop
over on 17th in Pennsylvania both of
their lives had had forbidden them from
smokings they would go over there and
smoke and then they split up well then
of course George becomes the deputy
director of the CIA he promotes John
several times John becomes deputy
director of the office I was in that he
becomes the senior CIA officer in
country in Riyadh then he becomes
George's chief of staff and then finally
deputy executive director of the CIA
which is the fourth ranking position in
the CIA needless to say John zold bought
on the analytic side he very quickly
forced into retirement hmm so John was
the number four in the CIA and then
became head of what was then called the
transnational tear
wrist Information Center it was meant to
be a standalone Bureau it later became
the National Counterterrorism Center and
then the Bush presidency ended in 2008
well at the CIA in 2008 everybody to
decide half the people went to John
McCain half the people went to Hillary
Clinton but one went to Barack Obama and
that happened to be John Brennan and
that's how John Brennan became a star
you know he was supposed to be named CIA
director in 2009 but progressive groups
jumped up and down and said wait a
minute this guy was the number for
ranking guy throughout the Bush
administration's torture program and he
wants us to believe that he didn't know
there was a torture program come on I
was sitting in that room 2 and I
remember John Brennan being there right
there's no way you didn't know about
that problem of course i think is not a
he was not one of the creators he wasn't
one of the designers for the
implementers but he was in on it so John
wasn't able to become CIA director in
2009 he had to wait for four years and
then became CIA director now a lot of
people have been asking me why he would
even respond to Donald Trump's attacks
and my answer I think is very simple
because John is like any other political
animal in Washington he knows Donald
Trump's not going to be President
forever but maybe John's going to be the
Secretary of Defense in the next
Democratic administration maybe he wants
to be the Secretary of State maybe he
wants to become the CEO of Halliburton
who knows but he's playing the the
hander in del which is quite a strong
hand yeah interest no that's an
interesting analysis and history they're
very fun history yeah but it's what's
your take on because Brennan did I mean
and in a very overt way for someone
who's in the intelligence community
because if people were looking for well
who's the intelligence community doesn't
like Donald Trump and it looks like
Brendan kind of offered himself to be
the face of that opposition he really is
brendan is the face of the anti-trump
faction within these diligence community
you know I never when I was first hired
into the CIA one of the rules was you
don't ever ever talk politics under any
circumstances because politics were
irrelevant to intelligence and it wasn't
until almost four years well almost
three years after my arrival it was the
morning of the 1992 election and my boss
said in our morning meeting he said
listen I know we're not supposed to do
this but I'm in curiosity could it you
guys vote for this morning and I'll
never forget it was 34 Bush 34 Clinton
and 24 / oh and I remember thinking wow
I'm not the only liberal here I just
assumed that I was there was one
incident i remember in 1996 where a
woman was ordered to take down a bob
dole bumper sticker that she had at her
desk because we were to be a political
right i mean you can love Bob Dylan when
you get home but not here at the office
a political oh that's that's all changed
the CIA has become very very political
and I think that started really under
george w bush people took very clearly
drawn sides and it continued through the
obama administration was that because
isn't like a post-911 polarization okay
not know know when people say that
everything changed on 911 they mean
literally everything changed on 911
especially inside the CIA and it's never
it's never gone back to you know the
September 10 CIA the agency's become
very politicized it's become a
paramilitary organization when in fact
it never was before again the role in
the CIA's recruit spies to steal secrets
and to do good analysis it's not to send
these these private armies around the
world to kill people that you don't like
or to implement your own special forces
policy or the drone strike policy which
was very I mean I almost feel like there
was some kind of
institutional push back to actually get
because at one point I mean talk about
paramilitary the sea I was running the
drone program and that or was part of
the process that was implementing the
kill list and that's not really
intelligence gathering that's I mean
that's extrajudicial assassination in
the case of some Americans gettin killed
but I mean it is not a weird role for
them to be kicking historically as a
former CIA officer I can neither confirm
nor deny the existence of a drug program
ok ok well fair enough I as a private
citizen will say it they're so random
people getting killed I don't know maybe
it's maybe it's all in my head ok so
moving on just to the situation where
people are trying to understand what's
happening with the CIA and Trump in this
very public fight I don't I mean what's
your read on at least clappers position
because he had a very interesting stance
he seemed to come out and talk about
this dossier this dolce by a former mi6
officer now private consultant
christopher i feel right i need all
these allegations which by the way i
just want to say you know I think
BuzzFeed put this out there and say this
is unverified and some of its factually
incorrect but here's the raw documents I
don't really think that's journalism
know it but but clapper kind of on the
one hand it was kind of a kiss of death
types is where he went out there to say
to try it seemed to help Trump but we
actually did was confirm that there had
been a briefing which put Trump back
into so can you talk about clappers
position and all this crap retrieves
very hard to walk this very fine
political line and he's just simply not
good at it and so you're right clapper
tried to briefly remain above the fray
one of the things that clever generally
does not do is to respond to attacks but
he's responded to attack several times
on this issue one of those deaths having
come from Donald Trump and I think
that's why John Brennan jump did John
Brennan has
for whatever reason a very deep-seated
hatred of Donald Trump and I think it's
because Trump has criticized him
publicly but for Brennan and clapper to
take sides on this to speak publicly
about this to either confirm or deny
rather than to say no comment the
dissociate even exist I think it's
unprecedented I won't say that I know
that mi6 officer Christopher steel I I
actually worked with him in London in
the early part of the last decade he is
a first-rate intelligence officer
absolutely first-rate he's a very
serious person I don't recall him being
even remotely political with that said
this whole story just strikes me is
crazy you know Donald Trump is a lot of
things but he's not stupid and I think
that trumps opponents and enemies have
consistently underestimated him from the
very beginning of the Republican
primaries through the general election
and it's not just in politics I'm
talking also about let's say this call
to the president of Taiwan you know
everybody said oh my god Trump doesn't
understand the one China policy he's
going to screw up relations with China
that have gone back to the next
administration she knew exactly what he
was doing and we underestimated him also
it's my experience that people here in
Washington including in the intelligence
community have found themselves in a
reactive mode to trunk rather than a
proactive one they find themselves
reacting to things that Trump says or
does and I think this may have been a
ham-handed attempt to try to be
proactive and it backfired Gaddafi I
itself or the clacker the leech of the
dossier and clappers comments about the
dossier either side of my question I
mean your positioning that are offering
an idea where it's just these people
aren't actually thinking this through
their just reacting with Trump other or
not I don't I drop thinking it through
I think John Brennan has has decided
that the notice of Russian intervention
is going to be his hammer that he's
going to hit Trump with all right so and
I wrote I wrote about this in the
article to the reader supported news
article so Brennan has come out and said
there was Russian intervention we have
this dossier on top of the Russian
intervention take my word for it well my
god everything that comes out of John
Brennan's mouth was a lie so why in the
world would we take his word for it I
saying the article the CIA told us they
weren't torturing that was a lie the CIA
told us there were no secret prisons
that was a lie the CIA says if they
weren't taking people to this dungeon in
Afghanistan called salt kit that was a
lie the CIA said that they weren't
cutting a metadata on the American
citizen that was a lie John Brennan
personally said we didn't we didn't back
into the Senate's computers that was a
lie and now he says I'm not lying I'm
telling you the truth so you should
believe me this time come on people are
still good but they're not that stupid
good point so okay that makes sense that
it's because I think from the outsiders
perspective what the public sees is
there's two ways to read it there's sort
of a competence or a sloppiness that
would be reacting and then there's other
people who are reading it and getting
very scared like oh my god the
intelligence community is completely
against this incoming president the
gambia outbreak of a inner conflict war
that could destabilize the federal
government I mean are you not afraid of
that or don't think that's a hella well
I'm not afraid of that I was on CNN last
week and asked me exactly the same
question and the response that I gave
was this what we're not talking about is
November 22nd 1963 scenario we're not
talking about that what we're talking
about is the CIA knows that they can
wait out this president because
presidents come and go and CIA people
there are there forever I mean look at
the people in leadership positions in
the CIA to have been there 25 years 30
years 35 years they're going to they're
going to see this president through and
he's going to go and somebody else was
going to come more to their liking so
what they do is they slow rule the
president
maybe they don't try to recruit the
toughest hardest sources maybe they
don't initiate that tough operation that
they've been considering they just slow
everything down and then four years from
now there may be another president and
they can ramp back up again I've also
said in the past that if there's one
thing that the CIA is good at it is
recruiting new presidents with a small
arm in recruiting what I mean is you get
a president elected Bill Clinton Barack
Obama immediately come to mind who has
no experience in intelligence right none
and maybe a little bit cynical about
intelligence and so the CIA begins
breathing him in the transition period
and when he sees his first blue border
report write something classified above
top secret or black border report eyes
only for the president of the
president-elect and when they start
briefing him about these incredibly well
placed clandestine sources that they
have around the world well they bring in
there and make him a part of a club he's
one of the guys now I know that they
hoped it but that's not happened with
Trump right kind of co-op to him but
it's not happening never know how to
respond to that you know when the news
first broke about this fight between
Trump and the agency I'm talking about
maybe six weeks ago my wife who was also
a senior CIA officer had been traveling
in the Middle East and she called me
from the Middle East and she said are
you watching this news about Trump and
the agency and I said I am and she said
this is bad and I said it is bad and she
said no I mean it's bad for the agency I
said it is because now they're not the
big dogs at the table now there's a
president in power who doesn't just
smile and nod and everything that they
say and thank them for their service and
thank them for their excellent
information now that the president is
saying I can still read you guys reckon
and also structurally here's the other
part of this it's one he doesn't have an
interest in saying the Russian hacking
story which is why they shouldn't be
playing it up there trying to co-opt and
because he's he's gonna do everything he
can to be legitimized that right also
seems to be and this goes to that
paragraph i quoted earlier in the
article you know Mike Flynn was the
former head of the DIA yeah and he has
from what i've read press accounts
you're probably better he has some
antagonism toward the CIA anyway boy
because this is CIA to every CIA officer
dia is a dumping ground for people who
weren't smart enough to make it into the
CIA and that's the basis of the
antagonism it was generations before dia
analysts where I even allowed the right
to the president's Daily Brief that was
the sole domain of the CIA until just
recently but I that's really the nature
of the antagonism because there's no
respect between the two organizations
but it doesn't that provide more fuel
for the idea that Trump is actually and
probably part of the antagonism recently
was going to he's actually going to go
after the CIA structurally which as as
commander-in-chief I mean yes you would
need Congress to go along and Congress
probably has a better relationship with
the CIA than he does at the moment at
least but he could still do some serious
damage I mean no sure he can't and you
know he made a statement just recently
saying that the CIA was bloated and
inefficient well you know what it is
bloated and into it and when a majority
of your operational staff is actually
sitting in cubicles in Langley Virginia
rather than that serving overseas
recruiting spies to steal those secrets
we were talking about you have a problem
and I think that's really what the CIA
is worried about with a trump presidency
you know we had clapper and Brennan
versus trump for a while there but then
clapper backed off yes he dropped out
who is really the boss the DNI or the
CIA director bono the DNI is not the
boss the DNI is simply a bureaucratic
stickers
and I say that for a couple of reasons
first of all despite the title Director
of National Intelligence the DNI does
not have the authority to appoint CIA
station chief that is the the sole
authority of the CIA director right so
the DNI isn't even informed when
somebody is being named station chief
overseas secondly the DN eyes Authority
comes with his budget but most of the
larger budgets within the intelligence
community are not controlled by the DNI
they're controlled by the Secretary of
Defense you know NSA has a massive
budget but DNI doesn't have any
authority over it govt has authority
over interface budget DoD has authority
over dia budget and Army Intelligence
navy intelligence air force intelligence
those all fall under DoD not DNI I mean
the whole purpose of D&I way it was
created by George W Bush was to put an
adult in charge of George tenant and
history because they had so screwed up
the organization post-911 so really it's
just another layer of bureaucracy that
affects only CIA but not the rest of the
intelligence community so what happened
when it seemed like clapper and brandon
were together against Trump and then
clapper retreated sethi of utter dismay
profound dismay at the leaks that went
out and he says we didn't produce that
right we did produce that and I don't
think we leaked it either I think
Brooklyn and we stand ready to serve you
which was a completely different message
did he break with Brennan at that point
yeah I think he could break with Brennan
keep in mind also and this is why I
oppose military officers in these senior
positions clappers in general and my
call general he has spent his entire
adult life saluting and saying yes sir
but you don't need somebody you don't
want somebody in those positions who's
just going to say yes sir you want
somebody who's going to say mr.
president that's a terrible idea and let
me tell you what somebody who can stand
up to a president
clapper can't stand up to a president
but brennan's a little bit more ornery
he's a little bit rougher and and
tougher frankly been clapper is and I
think that's why clappers dropped out
because it's not in his nature to
challenge a president or even a
president elect in public and for
Brendan Brendan doesn't care friends
from clarity I know a lot of guys just
like him what about Mike Pompeo do you
think he's up for challenging a
president the former the club nominee
for CIA director Mike Hayden knew who I
love said on CNN the other day that Mike
Pompeo only job is going to be to
protect CIA officers from Donald Trump
and that if he can do that he'll be a
successful CIA director i will say that
Mike Pompeo is crazy right-wing domestic
politics aside I have some highly placed
CIA friends who have briefed him many
many times and they say that he is
extraordinarily bright that he
understands the issues that he is wrong
on a couple of things like Iran for
example but he's somebody that they can
work with the key is is he going to see
the CIA rank-and-file as his
constituents or is he going to see the
truck White House as his constituent and
what agreements as he made to get the
appointment I mean Trump had to have
signed off obviously given Hughes's
nominee I imagine her told him hey these
guys are not our friends or I don't know
what Trump's informed him of or maybe
that happened before the outright public
fight but I imagine behind the scenes
Trump team was getting the impression
that CIA was not happy that they were
coming to town on january twentieth so I
wonder what private guarantees trunk
enforcement roads know from firsthand
experience I don't know but I can
speculate you know there have been two
events in the CIA history that CIA
officers called Friday night maskers one
was in October 1977 when
then CIA director Admiral stansfield
turner this is during the Carter
Administration just arbitrarily fired
something like a hundred and forty
officers from the director of operations
some of them just weeks away from
retirement he did it because the do had
failed they had failed on Iran and on a
couple of other major issues at the time
on terrorism and it was time for a clean
slate and he just fired them that was
probably a bad idea to just fire your
most experienced softly but that's what
he did and he did it on a Friday and
they call it the Friday night Massacre
the same thing happened in the very
beginning of the Clinton administration
and it was because and we're taking
parallel here now it was because Clinton
said that the CIA was bloated and
inefficient that there was a peace
dividend because there was no more
Soviet Union and we didn't need to spend
all this money spying on every single
country in the world he also did it on
Friday people were fired it's the second
Friday night master well done tom has
come out publicly and said that the CIA
is bloated and inefficient he's
certainly no friend of the CIA's
leadership as we've discussed and I
wouldn't be surprised if when he was
interviewing pompeo he said that his
vision for the CIA was more streamlined
more focused on overseas recruitment and
I want you to clean out headquarters and
get rid of all these operational people
who are doing operations and plus I mean
there has to be some kind of
restructuring if one is to take Trump's
foreign policy love that face which is
to say that he has a more realistic goal
if you like of foreign policy where he
does not believe in a lot of the liberal
interventionism or neoconservatism
everyone afraid he's not on the Bob keg
and train was really involved in these
promoting democracy through the barrel
of a gun so isn't he going to have to do
some culling no matter what because
there's a lot of people who have been in
the business of regime change in
democracy promotion anyway he will he
will every president put his stamp on
the CIA another thing about the CIA to
as with any big bureaucracy is that it's
constantly changing
stantly morphing no it changed a lot
more than it normally has the past under
Brennan because Brennan had a vision
where my he did away with the
geographical divisions and created these
so called fusion centers right so
instead of having a Middle East Division
of Southeast Division in Africa
dimension he has these bigger broader
Counterterrorism Center
counter-narcotics Center Counter
Intelligence Center and you bring
together operators and analysts and
maybe some science and technology people
and an admin staff and everybody works
together and it you know kumbaya well
that hasn't really worked and it had
been tried in the past you know Clinton
tried it there was even briefly an
environmental center because
environmental changes climate change
AIDS I mean these were all major events
that we're going to eventually impact
our national security and George W Bush
thought that was a stupid idea and did
away with those well oh he got word I
did not know that he got rid of the
death so there's no like Middle East
desk or North Africa desk e prime s
regretted did so who's responsible then
who takes responsibility when something
goes wrong exactly and nobody right
nobody I guess that does that couldn't
work out too well if you if I didn't
realize he had made those changes maybe
Trump well maybe the Trump's coming back
to a more nationalist realest school
he'll of course that's sort of a
question to he might try to clear house
because he wants a new mission set or a
new paradigm if you will it could be it
you know I hate what I hate when they
have to defend Donald Trump I just hate
but but comes right about this I mean
Britain's reorganization was a bad idea
it was bad for policy it was bad for the
agency it was just bad and it didn't
work and I think Trump wants to go back
to that original construct which is a
better idea but I guess the question
then is the original construct if he's
going to take away authority see there
it does seem to be one period of time
that people are harking to and I
understand you got a much more expertise
on this and the people
speculating on the internet but it was
you know arguably when because prompt
people compare Trump to mix it and there
was this sort of tensions as we all know
now mark felt was deep throat right it
was under and the people who did the
Watergate burglary and the quote-unquote
rat screwing across the country during
the Democratic primaries were CIA linked
so there was a sort of hidden bubbling
conflict and so I just wonder if there's
going to be if Trump's takes away
operational responsibility not
reorganizing and not paring down but
actually sort of says I don't want the
CIA to have when what else can they
throw at him I mean this dossier seem to
be like the worst they could come up
with that that would be the death knell
for the CIA if Trump took away
operational authority and gave it to it
would most logically go to the Defense
Department that would be the death knell
of the CIA that's the whole list of dead
from the CIA is to conduct operations
and if they no longer have that
authority then that would be the end of
it aren't they also in a bit of a power
struggle with JSOC and/or me is that
something you have no the agreements
that they've worked out with JSOC is
whenever the CIA wants to do a sensitive
operation involving JSOC like the bin
Laden killing for example they will
borrow JSOC forces so everybody involved
in the operation is active duty stuff
but they're under CIA auspices so it's
technically a CIA operation even though
nobody actually on the ground is a CIA
officer right right and that's kind of
interesting because this is a new field
that I think you see the intelligence
agencies struggling to get in which is
cyber war yeah and what was revealed and
I know you're going to have problems
talking about this I'll just say what
was revealed with some of the reporting
on Olympic Games Stuxnet was it was a US
Cyber Command which is at Fort Meade now
where the NSA is but the CIA got their
beaks wet if you will by getting in
there and having a sort of
administrative authority over the NSA
meaning before the NSA would launch
attack on the tongs or whatever there be
a CIA office
who would actually have to authorize it
so it was under you it was inside US
Cyber Command with an NSA operative
designing the weapons of the programs of
the operations and then a CIA a person
they were tasked with basically having
administrative control which I guess
created some kind of accountability
because who tis okay well yes again I
say designing all these programs but
they can't actually launch each one you
know the tailored operations unless a
CIA officer tells them they can yeah i'm
going to preface my comments by saying
that the complete extent of my knowledge
of Stuxnet is from the new york times in
the washington post I know absolutely
nothing behind the scenes on the Stuxnet
virus but I can tell you that it would
make sense that that that operation
would be under CIA auspices because NSA
is a more of a passive collection agency
it's not an offensive operations agency
they don't put officers on the ground to
infect computers to recruit sources to
do these things that have to be done by
a human being oh okay because that's
interesting because the way you read it
when they talk about tailored operations
is that NSA actually has operatives
doing these things they're saying when
they take talent operations they have
people tailoring operations creating
these things and the actual people who
implement the weapons whether that means
putting a flash drive on somewhere or
whatever is a CIA operative correct they
don't have any human resources to do
these operations of CIO every once
awhile on a TV show like blacklist for
example they'll talk about an NSA agent
and I've chuckled to myself there is no
such thing ah interesting ok so then CIA
doesn't have to worry that much see I
was wondering if there was such an anti
CIA position the Trump administration
and Flynn's in there who knows how to
see the problem with they gotta worry
about is maybe they have a lot of
antagonism with Trump maybe he's pissed
off at them but he doesn't know where to
put the knife in Flynn knows were too
high so nice right he does because four
is been screwed by the agency in the
past
and slim has had a difficult personal
relationship with Brennan so there's
there's zero love loss between Flynn and
the CIA this is going to be a rough
relationship even after and it will be
gone even though Brennan will be gone
because don't forget that Brennan over
the past four years has been promoting
all of his acolytes up through the ranks
and now they're the ones at the senior
most levels of the senior intelligence
service who are going to take over the
day-to-day operations of the CIA so even
though Brennan is gone the CIA is still
being run by Brennan's people yeah that
was one of my question what happens when
the higher-ups leave you know do they
still have influence somebody just
recently said once CIA all a CIA or you
know what role did a these directors
play well after they retire Oh literally
none they even lose their security
clearances retired directors are allowed
to maintain a secret security clearance
I can tell you when I was an analyst
everyone still while a retired director
would come to the agency kind of for
funny reasons and I was instructed to
brief them or have lunch with them in
the director's dining room and I was
warned repeatedly don't go over the
secret level I'll give you an example
avril Turner who I spoke about a little
while ago stansfield turner he and his
wife were invited onto an
around-the-world cruise for free and in
exchange he had to give four lectures on
Middle Eastern politics so I was
instructed to brief him on and this is
in the early 90s on pro-democracy
movements in the Middle East right so we
met three times for lunch in the
director's dining room he took copious
notes but I had to keep my briefing to
the secret level and then I would say
that's classified that's not classified
as I got from the papers if I got from
wherever and he made sure to write down
only the unclassified information and
that's what he used to give his speech
on the cruise ships but if there was
anything top secret or anything
involving human intelligence we're not
even allowed to brief it to the retired
directors and that's why people like
George Tenet for example
has nothing whatsoever to do with the
CIA anymore George Tenet works for a
venture capital firm in New York City
doing vulture transactions he has
nothing to do with intelligence oh no
you didn't you tell no not even a detail
which was his baby right that's not yeah
so Brennan will have no influence
technically but his team is essentially
still him left behind because they have
all the same sentiments loyalty school
everything like that that's often so if
there is a purge by pompeo it'll be of
the Brenna nights it would be yes it
would and then so he can create his own
legacy of tenant if Brennan is tenant
legacy Pompey will be bringing a whole
new crew of people to be his legacy and
there's a precedent for this too in in
1981 January of 81 Ronald Reagan wanted
to clean the CIA out and get rid of all
the Carter people so normally a
president comes in and he named the CIA
director and a deputy director but what
Casey did when when Reagan name's Casey
CIA director Casey names his own deputy
director but then Casey also named his
own deputy director for operations video
who happened to be a businessman with no
intelligence experience at all know that
oftentimes doesn't work because the
businessman has no idea what he's
getting into but sometimes you really do
need a purge and I could see Trump
coming to the decision that he needs a
purge don't forget all these people and
it's not just those at the very top but
down at the bottom level of the senior
intelligence service the people leading
a group chief or hire people younger
than I am they all came of age under
Barack Obama and so even if they're not
in any way political they still came of
age under obama and brennan and Petraeus
and you know I
if Trump wants to start fresh he can
make it ugly and start fresh I could see
him doing it I think he's signaling it
but they can only get two he hasn't come
right out and said it but I think that I
think we would be foolish to not think
that there had been conversations
between Trump and Flynn and popeo about
how do we clear this place out and start
over again and these latest spats over
this dossier and the Russian hacking the
role of Russian hacking I mean if you
were if you were trying not to get her
down this would be the last thing you
should be trying to do so this would be
the last thing you'd want to do it or
maybe be a little conspiratorial maybe
it was they started a fight with the CIA
so they could rationalize the purge I
don't know but what a great Russian
covert operation that would be how do I
get how do we get that the CIA purge and
then look they've done it I mean I'm not
saying it was the Russians but how
interesting i mean this is something you
could you know write books about or how
did this thus credit this yeah i mean
who exactly who's done more i mean if it
was a Russian up they all they want to
do is just described the CIA they would
have succeeded immensely because now
you've got people it's all mixed up
because I see people and you know on
social media else work defending the CIA
who are left yes and then you have
people on the right who hate the CIA now
and they were their traditional
supporters it's just crazy it's bizarro
world reverse world yeah two more things
they seem to me to be acting more like I
mean doesn't have to be CIA could be
anywhere in station you know like a
creature sort of and it escalates when
one action doesn't work then you know
the next week the next friday nights are
we something else they will try
something else Timmy they act like
Brandon whoever else is involved seem to
be acting like people who are threatened
but that's just a an uninformed opinion
but I do have one more question that
happened over the last couple days
President Obama's presser there are a
couple people reading more than a couple
people reading something into this
something that he said the quote is
he said so with respect to WikiLeaks I
don't see a contradiction first of all I
haven't commented on Wikileaks generally
the conclusions of the intelligence
community with respect to the Russian
hacking were not conclusive as to
whether WikiLeaks was winning or not in
being the conduit through which we heard
about the DFC email that were reached
and it's a long quote but I see people
reading something into the WikiLeaks
witting or not as the conduit and that
last thing emails that were elite it
seems from people saying oh he just
admitted they were leaks not hat right I
read it that way I thought it was a bad
use of the word me I don't care what I
think he didn't mean to to definitively
say that they were released seeing it
like published right yeah well that's
what I think of points are joint like
what what is the CIA's view of wikileaks
I imagine it's very I mean I'm sure they
hate WikiLeaks but it has to be one of
ya of deep hatred now no CIA documents
have ever been leaked to WikiLeaks right
you go through you go through the chump
demanding cash and it's all really
low-level State Department diplomatic
cables some low-level military stuff a
lot of expressly was unclassified it was
press but there's not a single CIA
document in there so I think the CIA
hates WikiLeaks for what it is but
there's no personal grudge against
Julian Assange I think because he's
never damaged or harmed the CIA in any
way hey can I add one more thing to
please need to be Joanne's a comment
about the leak um you know Craig Murray
the former British ambassador to his
Becca stands a member of veteran
intelligence professionals for sanity
has told the British press that he was
the conduit to WikiLeaks right he says
that there was no Russian hack that it
was a whistleblower inside the DNC he
won't say who it was
who took the documents and gave them to
craig and craig gave them to WikiLeaks
now why the mainstream media has utterly
ignored this I have no idea because
Craig Murray is one of the most highly
respected whistleblowers in the UK
demands an ambassador a decorated
ambassador and he's telling us that
there was no hack well and that may be
that you could talk about this for a
second just because I want to keep you
too long but what is up and it's because
of your what you just raised which is
the press is so invested in this new
Cold War yeah this tension with Russia
and I can't figure out if it's sort of a
reverberation of the Clinton campaign
shoving all this talking point into
their brains during the campaign and
they can't let go if it's sport you know
people who are still pissed off if it's
just a group of people want to discredit
Trump but there is this I agree like I
saw that report i was very interesting
other than sean hannity yes which is a
crazy I've my mind's made up bizarro
world develops other than it's been
completely ignored and instead they have
continually rashes up the tensions with
Russia it seems like they have a like
this is an agenda to get it to get US
Russia to being a conflict yes thinking
what do you make of that getting exactly
the same thing it's like it's like for
whatever reason the left is not going to
be happy unless there's this new
conflict with Russia but but nobody has
accused the Russian of actually throwing
the election nobody has accused the
Russian of packing into polling machines
voting machines and switching votes or
hacking into the SEC or two state
Electoral Commission so what exactly is
it that the Russians are supposed to
have done I'm not really clear on that
and besides if there was a real hack and
bill Binney says this all the time and
he's exactly right because he's one of
the country's foremost authorities on
this issue if there was a hack
regardless of how good the Russians were
there would be an electronic trail
that goes right back to the Russians and
there is no electronic trail if there
was an athame CIA would tell us so and
then have it what they're telling us is
take our word for it but and also about
Obama's quote there one of the things
that really bother me about it was when
he says you know the conclusions of the
intelligence community with respect to
the Russian hacking we're not conclusive
as to whether WikiLeaks was winning or
not in being the conduit and then also
there's a McClatchy article yesterday
about oh well they've been investigating
this is the spring and we think that a
the Russian pension system was used to
funnel money to hackers and I mean
basically if you believe that Craig's
mary says I'm basically facilitated this
exchange you know it's sort of employing
to heat a Russian operative of some time
right after Russian dangerous which is
ridiculous because why would he offer is
say oh yeah the Bob yes your I know I
think they're just still digging for
something that people might believe yeah
we got work out that's our bed end so
any closing thoughts John before we go
or no you know like you like I always
say with shadow proof thank you for what
you guys do and what you have done in
the past shadow proof and before
shatterproof firedoglake was where I
published my letters from Loreto my blog
from prison I owe you guys a debt of
gratitude and I'm always happy to speak
with you thank you so much we feel the
same way and thank you for giving us
time today make the coffee it's a legend
a good one bye bye bye
okay that's our show well thank you for
listening and special thank you to John
Kerry ocular guess read his work at the
reader supported news.com I want to ask
you to please support the show at
patreon actually on.com flash around the
Empire five dollars a month let's put on
the show questions comments or just want
to yell at me standard shatterproof calm
and please see Joanne and my work at
shatterproof back down see you next time
[Music]
you